<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: free-speech | My Geekdom]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/categories/free-speech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-06T20:30:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neil Smithline]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SOPA DOA? Not Quite But Getting There]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/01/14/SOPA-DOA/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-14T00:18:39-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/01/14/SOPA-DOA</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
While not dead, SOPA is losing its teeth. Despite having had its major backer remove one of the more totalitarian portions from the bill (the ability to block non-US DNS addresses), SOPA appears unable to make progress in Congress. 
</p>


<p>
In a <a href="http://cnet.co/ArcHPH">CNET</a> article (via <a href="http://bit.ly/zMTg3h">Slashdot</a>), the <a href="#wiki-RIAA">RIAA</a> whines:
</p>


<blockquote>

<p>Instead of helping to come up with mechanisms to deny access to
the U.S. market by foreign criminals," the RIAA wrote, "the
opposition just keeps saying no. It is incumbent upon them to help
develop language that will ensure that criminals can't access our
market, while at the same time protecting our need for national
cybersecurity.
</p>
</blockquote>




<p>
As <a href="#SOPA-the-end-of-free-speech.org">discussed previously</a>, SOPA claims to support American businesses while it really supports the very large media companies and stifles smaller companies and individuals rights to publish.
</p>


<p>
As I've stated in my previous <a href="#SOPA-the-end-of-free-speech.org">posting about SOPA</a>, I am strongly opposed to <a href="#wiki-Piracy-of-software">piracy</a> as I am a software engineer (ie: software pays my rent). But I also believe that piracy can be dealt with without destroying <a href="#wiki-Freedom_of_speech">free speech</a>. My viewpoints are similar to those of the <a href="#wiki-Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">EFF</a> and differ from the <a href="#wiki-Free_Software_Foundation">FSF</a>'s viewpoint which opposes proprietary software altogether.
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Florida Appeals Court More Liberal Than SOPA!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/30/florida-beats-sopa/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-30T12:26:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/30/florida-beats-sopa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Earlier this week, the Florida appeals court made a ruling that even the poster of a defamatory posting on a public website could not force a website to remove the posting. While most sites allow you to remove your own postings, <a href="http://www.ripoffreport.com/">RipoffReport.com</a>, the site involved in this ruling, states that as an advocate of free speech, it never removes reports. This is clearly stated at the top of their home page and documented extensively on their <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ripoff_Report#Non-removal_Policy">Wikipedia page</a>. 
<!-- more -->
</p>


<p> 
While not allowing the poster to remove or have removed a posting seems extreme, the site claims that it wishes to remain unbiased. As such, it makes no judgment calls about its content. Everything that is appropriate for the site will stay on the site, forever. RipoffReport.com is afraid that posters may be pressured by 3^rd-parties to remove articles. As such, They are simply not allowed to.
</p>


<p>
While postings are never removed, the site allows anyone to post a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rebuttal">rebuttal</a> to any posting. A poster can use this mechanism to retract their initial statement. 
</p>


<p>
The court ruled that RipoffReport.com could neither be held liable for the defamatory posting nor be forced to remove it. The bottom line of all of this is that
</p>




<div style="text-align: center">
<p>The supreme court of Florida, a <a href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/125066/State-States.aspx">middle-of-the-road state</a>, was willing to make a controversial ruling favored many aspects of freedom of speech. If SOPA is passed, cases like this won't even make it to courts as SOPA make it clear that if a ruling is defamatory, it is illegal.
</p>
</div>




<p>
While Congress has delayed voting on SOPA for another month, it is still on the docket. It is unclear what the fate of SOPA will be. 
</p>


<p>
One can hope that Congress pays attention to protests such as the statement]] consumers sent to <a href="http://www.godaddy.com">GoDaddy</a> after it announced its support of SOPA. GoDaddy announced that on a Saturday (see <a href="http://news.slashdot.org/story/11/12/29/2053252/wikipedia-to-dump-godaddy-over-sopa">more complete chronology</a>) and then lost <a href="http://tech.slashdot.org/story/11/12/25/1452251/go-daddy-loses-over-21000-domains-in-one-daylosing">21K domains</a> on the next day. More recently, the <a href="http://news.slashdot.org/story/11/12/29/2053252/wikipedia-to-dump-godaddy-over-sopa">Wikipedia announced it would discontinue all use of GoDaddy</a>. 
</p>


<p>
Let's continue to hope that advocates of free speech, including you (see <a href="#id-06BB29E4-D6B3-430E-B5A3-FDC6716A0ED3">SOPA: The End Of Free Speech</a> for instructions as to how to help), continue to pressure our government into sane activit
</p>


<p>
Copied directly from the <a href="http://www.slashdot.org">Slashdot</a> <a href="http://bit.ly/vVVDLC">article</a>:
</p>


<blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.ripoffreport.com/">RipoffReport.com</a> contained an admittedly defamatory posting, by one of its users, about a person who operated a Florida corporation providing addiction treatment services. Although the site was asked by the poster herself to remove the post, it refused. A Florida appeals court has ruled that the site is absolutely immune from suit (<a href="http://recordingindustryvspeople.blogspot.com/2011/12/florida-appeals-court-rules.html">pdf</a>), and cannot even be directed to remove the offending post, since under the [[http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode47/usc_sec_47_00000230-&mdash;000-.html][Communications Decency Act (47 USC 230)] 'no cause of action may be brought' against a provider of an "interactive computer service" based upon information provided by a 3rd party.
</p>
</blockquote>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Corporate Censorship In The Digital Age]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/27/pravda/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-27T08:58:30-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/27/pravda</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div id="outline-container-1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-1">Measuring Freedom</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1">

<p>While I'll leave it to historians and politicians to debate the validity of this statement, IMO, a country's freedom can be understood by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guesstimation">guestimating</a> the answers two simple questions:
</p><ol>
<li>How freely the citizens are allowed to travel &ndash; both within their country as well as in-and-out of their country.
</li>
<li>How freely the government allows information to be dispersed.
</li>
</ol>


<p>
While this posting only focuses on freedom of information, I mention the above because I feel that it is important to keep in mind how critical freedom of information is. 
</p>
<p>
When free information flow is impacted, it does not matter whether it is censored by a totalitarian government to control the thoughts of its people or a search provider to stay out of trouble legal troubles (see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/">Wikipedia</a>'s article on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criticism_of_Google#Censorship">Google Censorship</a> and <a href="http://technorati.com/technology/article/google-censorship-rising-faster-than-ever/">recent statistics</a> about Google's censoring)<sup><a class="footref" name="fnr.1" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup>.
<!-- more -->

</p></div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-2" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-2">Recent Attempts At Total Information Control</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2">

<p>During the heat of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold_War">cold war</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pravda#The_Soviet_period">Pravda</a>, <i>The</i> official newspaper of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet_Union">Soviet Union</a>'s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist_Party_of_the_Soviet_Union">Communist Party</a>, was well-known for distributing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propaganda">propaganda</a> while, at the same time, the Soviet Union also restricted all non-official forms of information distribution. Today, China's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_firewall">Great Firewall</a> and its government-managed <a href="http://tech.slashdot.org/story/11/12/26/2217215/chinas-parallel-online-universe">substitution of popular web sites</a> are attempts at total information control.
</p>
<p>
While not directly relevant to this article, the Soviet Union used to inhibit and China currently inhibits the free movement of their citizens. That is, they score poorly on both of the <a href="#Measuring-Freedomns">above questions</a>.
</p>
</div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-3" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-3">America's Current Loss Of Freedom<sup><a class="footref" name="fnr.2" href="#fn.2">2</a></sup></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-3">

<p>Whatever its benefits may be, any honest review of laws such as <a href="http://neilsmithline.com/archives/2011/12/11/sopa_the_end_of_free_speech/index.htmlSOPA">SOPA</a> must state that they will lead to a reduction in information dispersal. Opinions about the exact quantity and quality of information dispersal reduction varies greatly. The protractors state that the intent of the law is to reduce illegal content dispersal (ie: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_piracy">piracy</a>).
</p>
<p>
But it is more difficult to understand how <a href="http://google.com">Google</a> and <a href="http://apple.com">Apple</a> have, I suspect unintentionally, teamed up with <a href="http://microsoft.com">Microsoft</a> to seriously threaten the dispersal of information. Restricting information dispersal isn't their goal Their goal is corporate success. But when it comes to basic human rights such as information dispersal, motivation doesn't really seem important.
</p>
</div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-4" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4">Brief History Lesson (especially for people who don't remember life before the web)</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4">

<p>In America, information dispersal used to rely on America's famous <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom_of_the_press">Freedom Of The Press</a>. Public awareness as to the degree of control <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_business">big business</a> plays in the <i>free</i> press has been growing for a century or more. Besides the growth in public awareness, the press has been increasingly controlled by big business (think pre- and post-<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Randolph_Hearst#Yellow_journalism">Hearst</a>). But when things were looking the bleakest, out of nowhere, the internet came to the rescue.
</p>
<p>
In perhaps the only prediction of the internet's future that has come true, the web allowed average people to become publishers. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blog">Blogs</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podcasts">podcasts</a> (popularized by and named for Apple's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/iPod">iPod</a>), and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</a> (now owned by Google) have truly enabled any person with access to a computer to publish their opinion, however inaccurate, insane, or just plain stupid that might be. The growth of the web led to an ensuing INFORMATION OVERLOAD. While this had a negative impact on people's access to the information they desire, people and technology seem to have managed it.
</p>
</div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-5" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-5">The Current Problem</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-5">

<p>The basic problem is that today, information storage, editing and dispersal occurs in just a few ways:
</p><ol>
<li>Traditional media such as newspaper, cable TV, and <i>&lt;yawn&gt;</i> broadcast TV.
</li>
<li>Desktop <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operating_system">operating systems</a>: This includes Windows and Mac OS X.
</li>
<li>Mobile operating systems: This includes <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ios">iOS</a> on Apple's iPhones and iPads, Google's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a> on mobile phones and tablets as well as their <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ChromeOS">ChromeOS</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/netbook">netbooks</a>, Microsoft's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Phone">Windows Phone</a>, etc&hellip;
</li>
<li>Internet-based <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_storage">Cloud Storage</a>: Of the nine <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_storage#Examples_of_cloud_storage">examples</a> of cloud storage on the <a href="http:wikipedia.com">Wikipedia</a> at the time of writing this article, four of them belong to Google, Microsoft, or Apple. 
</li>
<li>Other online storage: Microsoft's <a href="http://hotmail.com">Hotmail</a> and Google's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gmail">Gmail</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_docs">Docs</a>, YouTube, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blogger">Blogger</a>, and numerous other services run by these three companies provide many other forms of cloud storage.
</li>
<li>SOCIAL WEB SITES: specifically FACEBOOK and TWITTER. While not yet a seriously contender, Google is trying to muscle its way into this market with GOOGLE+ and previously GOOGLE BUZZ.
</li>
<li>SEARCH ENGINES: Search engines are the digital compasses that point people to information.
</li>
<li>ONLINE REFERENCES: While I don't have any statistics, I imagine that the Wikipedia is the largest online reference. Other sites such as IMDB and DICTIONARY.com are also significant players. To a lesser extent, sites such as GOOGLE SCHOLARS and EXPEDIA cannot be discounted.
</li>
</ol>


<p>
While this is an incomplete list of a collection of different types of data-related companies, it is clear that Microsoft, Apple, and Google are dominant in this arena.
</p>
<p>
In addition to the above, the actual means of information delivery is via <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_browsers">web browsers</a> and a collection of less-important applications such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/iTunes">iTunes</a> and the seemingly infinite collection of TWITTER CLIENTS.
</p>
</div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-6" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-6">The Freedom Crisis</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-6">

<p>   Of the major players discussed in the <a href="#sec-5">previous section</a>, only two of them meet any reasonable definition of INDEPENDENT: The Wikipedia<sup><a class="footref" name="fnr.3" href="#fn.3">3</a></sup> and the Firefox browser. Every other major player is a for-profit company. While companies such as Facebook and Twitter attempt allow uncensored content to be published by users, they are still for-profit companies.
</p>
<p>
Out of the for-profit companies, Google, Apple, and Microsoft are dominant in numerous categories. They are certainly happy to throw their weight around. 
</p><ul>
<li>Apple has been trying to <a href="http://apple.slashdot.org/story/11/08/09/1832254/sale-of-samsung-galaxy-tab-blocked-in-the-eu">destroy Samsung's mobile market</a> by presenting <a href="http://yro.slashdot.org/story/11/08/15/1758224/flawed-evidence-in-eu-apple-vs-samsung-case">falsified evidence</a> to courts.
</li>
<li>A question about <a href="http://apple.slashdot.org/story/11/12/27/0216217/techrights-recommends-an-apple-boycott">boycotting Apple</a> has made the front page of <a href="http://slashdot.org">Slashdot</a>. If you are unfamiliar with the great influence of Slashdot, reading about the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slashdot_effect">Slashdot Effect</a> should give you some perspective.
</li>
<li>Google tried to shut down <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CyanogenMod">Cyanogen(mod)</a>, a replacement for Google's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a> mobile operating system.
</li>
<li>This <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=microsoft+lawsuit&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;aq=t&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:unofficial&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;tbs=qdr:y">Google search</a> for <i>Microsoft lawsuits</i> returns 24 million hits for the past year.
</li>
<li>While only indirectly related, <a href="http://www.godaddy.com">GoDaddy.com</a>, the <a href="http://support.google.com/a/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=47610">preferred</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_registrar">domain registrar</a> for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Sites">Google Sites</a>, has <a href="http://yro.slashdot.org/index2.pl?fhfilter=godaddy">hit Slashdot's home page</a> five times in the past three days.
</li>
</ul>



</div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-7" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-7">Footnotes</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-7">


<p>
But the same site has seemingly super-human, volunteer moderators that monitor and remove links to PROPRIETARY SOFTWARE. This <a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=935185">example</a> is just the first hit I found from a quick Google search. In addition to the site's speedy moderators, the very active user community also helps to regulate postings on the site (see the <a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showpost.php?p=11020601&amp;postcount=7">seventh posting</a> on the above page). 
</p>
<p>
The XDA-Developers' community clearly appreciates the freedom the site provides while respecting the legal rights of software owners and the difficulties challenging those rights can cause the site.
</p>


<a title="Just Give: Wikipedia" href="http://wikimediafoundation.org/w/index.php?title=WMFJA085/en/US&amp;utm_source=JustGive&amp;utm_medium=sidebar&amp;utm_campaign=20110130SB003&amp;language=en&amp;uselang=en&amp;country=US&amp;referrer=http%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fwiki%2FUser:NeilSmithline"><img width="305" height="117" src="http://www.neilsmithline.com//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/1d/Wikipedia-world-info-229x88.png" alt="Click to vote for free information"/></a>

<div id='footnotes'>
<h4 class='footnotes'>Footnotes: </h4>
<div id='text-footnotes'>
<p class="footnote"><sup><a class="footnum" name="fn.1" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> Please note that I am a believer of <i>reasonable</i> restrictions on intellectual property. For example, I consider <a href="http://www.xda-developers.com/">XDA-Developers</a> to be one of the most liberal content distributors. Their site is full of ways to hack, modify, and replace the software that comes on mobile phones. They have successfully battled legal challenges from both Microsoft and Google.
</p>


<p class="footnote"><sup><a class="footnum" name="fn.2" href="#fnr.2">2</a></sup> I have limited this article to freedom in America. While I feel the issues I raise are universal, I do not feel I have enough knowledge to speak confidently about other countries so I have omitted them.
</p>


<p class="footnote"><sup><a class="footnum" name="fn.3" href="#fnr.3">3</a></sup> Have you donated your $5 to the Wikipedia? Have you ever edited the Wikipedia? <i>Free</i> speech isn't free. The next time you find a typo in the Wikipedia, either correct it or add a note to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk_page#Talk_page">Talk</a> page. The Talk page is a great place to point out a problem when you are lacking the time, knowledge, or motivation to correct the page. While I am far from a major contributor to the Wikipedia, my <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/Neil_Smithline">contribution page</a> shows that I have edited pages across a wide range of topics &ndash; many that I really know nothing about.  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Neil_Smithline">user page</a> or just give&hellip;
</p></div>
</div>

</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vote With Your Money: Blackball GoDaddy For Propagandizing SOPA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/23/blackball-godaddy/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-23T07:58:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/23/blackball-godaddy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<a href="http://godaddy.com">GoDaddy</a> has just released its <a href="http://support.godaddy.com/godaddy/go-daddys-position-on-sopa/?isc=smtwsup">official statement</a> (via <a href="http://yro.slashdot.org/story/11/12/23/0253207/godaddy-backs-sopa">Slashdot</a> via <a href="http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/271730/20111222/sopa-bill-2012-godaddy-reveals-support.htm">ibtimes.com</a>) on SOPA. You can read my opinions on SOPA in my recent blog posting <a href="#id-06BB29E4-D6B3-430E-B5A3-FDC6716A0ED3">SOPA: The End Of Free Speech</a>. While I can't imagine the business logic that motivated GoDaddy, I respect the free publication of opinions contrary to my own. In fact, my objections to <a href="https://wfc2.wiredforchange.com/o/9042/p/dia/action/public/?action_KEY=8173">SOPA</a> are that it allows corporations to prohibit contrary opinions. Should SOPA pass, GoDaddy, if they chose to worry about lil' ol' me, could, with the effort of a single letter, have my blog shut down for posting about this article.
<!-- more -->

While SOPA provides real teeth for corporations to control any use of their name, it will continue to allow companies to state, or misstate, legal facts. As such, GoDaddy has published its "<a href="http://support.godaddy.com/godaddy/go-daddys-position-on-sopa/?isc=smtwsup">official statement</a>" about SOPA that is simply loaded with &lt;insert your favorite term for BS here&gt;.
</p>




<div id="outline-container-1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-1">Good Intentions</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1">


<p>    
    In our view, Internet policy should strive to balance the sometimes competing goals of the global free flow of information (which is clearly critical to U.S. businesses), with enforcement of the rule of law. We don't see those competing goals as mutually exclusive, but rather, complimentary. In fact, that balance is essential to a flourishing, yet safe, Internet.
</p>
<p>
Why some members of the Internet ecosystem do not believe it is their responsibility to participate in finding that balance is unclear to us. We've found that balance in the past in the child protection and counterfeit pharmaceuticals contexts, for example, where we voluntarily take action against customers whose websites or domain names violate the law. So far, none of our voluntary action has stifled legitimate capitalism online. And neither will robust intellectual property enforcement.
</p>
<p>
The question should be how, not whether, we develop a notice and takedown regime in a responsible and responsive way. At Go Daddy, we are proud of our best practices and believe that they exemplify a model for the rest of the ecosystem. In 2010, we voluntarily took action and shut down more than 30,000 illegal online pharmacies. And, I spend a great deal of my working (and non-working) hours each day working to keep the Internet a better and safer place, especially for children.
</p>
<p>
And we are responsive to intellectual property holders, even absent a clear mandate by Congress to take action.
</p></div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SOPA: The End Of Free Speech]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/11/SOPA-the-end-of-free-speech/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-11T00:31:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2011/12/11/SOPA-the-end-of-free-speech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> 
<a href="https://wfc2.wiredforchange.com/o/9042/p/dia/action/public/?action_KEY=8173">SOPA</a>, and its sister bill PROTECT-IP, are currently making their way
through congress. I have pointers to some of the excellent sources of
information on the bills at the end of this article.
</p>


<p>
While the magnitude of these bills is staggering, this posting focuses
on how the passage of these bills will dramatically remove the ability
of individuals to produce and share content on the internet.
</p>


<p>
While I favor reasonable enforcement and punishment of internet-based
crimes, these bills introduce the concepts of:
</p>


<ul>
<li><b>Guilty until proven innocent</b> 
</li>
<li><b>Guilty by association</b> 
</li>
<li><b>Whoopsy daisy legal recourse</b> that restricts damages (eg: going bankrupt) due to abuse of SOPA to
  "s&mdash; happens" response.
</li>
</ul>




<p>
into American law. At least to me, those concepts don't seem very
"American".
<!-- more -->

The problems with this bill can best be demonstrated by a simple
example. Let us use the consider a fictitious, non-profit website run
by a couple of friends that is focused on internet freedom. The
website is called <i>Big Brother, Back-off and Stop-It!</i> with the URL
BBBandS.org.
</p>


<p>
If this bill is passed, <i>Big Brothers Big Sisters</i> (<a href="http://bbbs.org">http://bbbs.org</a>)
could simply write a letter to search engines such as Google, content
distributors such as Facebook, and payment companies such as Paypal,
claiming that they feel BBBandS.org is infringing on their <i>domain name</i>. Once this is done, <i>each</i> search, content, and payment provider
must contact BBBandS.org (remember that BBBandS.org is a couple of
friends working out of their garage).
</p>


<p>
BBBandS.org must reply to each and every provider explaining why they
do not feel that BBBandS.org is infringing on BBBS.org's <i>domain name</i>. It seems clear that BBBandS.org could not accomplish this task
in a timely fashion.
</p>


<p>
For each company that BBBandS.org does not manage to provide a
credible counterclaim to (where <i>credible</i> is determined by the
search, content, and payment provider companies), a fairly mechanical
process will begin where federal courts will execute a <i>cease and desist</i> to each search, content, or payment service provider
informing them that they must stop servicing BBBandS.org.
</p>


<p>
<b>Guilty until proven innocent:</b> Note that the
simple lack of a timely response to sufficient to, by means of a
judicial <i>cease and desist</i> order, force search, and payment providers to
become legally and financially liable if they continue to do business
with BBBandS.org. 
</p>


<p>
<b>Guilty by association:</b> Whether a service provider agrees or disagrees
with the order, they can be held accountable if they do not "block
access to or end financial affiliation" with BBBandS.org.
</p>


<p>
To add insult to injury, the bill goes on to provide "immunity from
liability for service providers" that follow a <i>cease and desist</i>
order, causing clear economic harm to BBBandS.org, <b>even</b> if it is
eventually determined that there was no infringement.
</p>


<p>
<b>Whoopsy daisy legal recourse</b>: Should the <i>cease and desist</i> order
be determined to be incorrect via a legal process that may take years
and cost more money than most people will ever have, this bill
restricts BBBandS.org's legal recourse to accepting the apologies of
the US judicial system.
</p>


<p>
While I am in favor of what the bill claims to be protecting, this
bill proposes far too high a price to pay for that protection.
</p>


<p>
If you care about the rights of small organizations (eg: people like you), please:
</p>


<ul>
<li>Read an excellent summary of SOPA in this <a href="https://wfc2.wiredforchange.com/o/9042/p/dia/action/public/?action_KEY=8173">article</a>. Keep in mind
    that the reason that the article seems ludicrous, insane, and
    unbelievable is because it is accurately reflecting the proposed
    legislation.
</li>
<li>Google <i>SOPA</i> or <i>PROTECT-IP</i>.
</li>
<li>Take action via Mozilla's page <a href="http://bit.ly/tvIpE3">focused on this issue</a>.
</li>
<li>Take action via the <a href="https://wfc2.wiredforchange.com/o/9042/p/dia/action/public/?action_KEY=8173">EFF</a>.
</li>
<li>Contact your legislator using <a href="http://bit.ly/s0I5me">this</a> <a href="#OpenCongress.org">OpenCongress.org</a> page (takes
    only a minute or so).
</li>
<li>Discuss this issue with everyone you know.
</li>
<li>Discuss this issue with people you don't know. I recommend "So what do you think
    about SOPA?" as a pick-up line though I encourage creativity and
    individualism as to the exact wording.
</li>
<li>Post a copy or a link to one or more articles on SOPA everywhere
    you can.
</li>
</ul>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
