<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: smartphones | My Geekdom]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/categories/smartphones/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-21T21:53:04-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neil Smithline]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bookifying News]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/07/15/bookifying-news/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-15T10:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/07/15/bookifying-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div id="outline-container-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-1">Bookifying News</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">

<p>I frequently find it convenient to take a <i>website on the road</i>. That is, I want a website or part of a website in a convenient, portable, easily accessible format on my <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asus_Eee_Pad_Transformer">Asus Transformer</a> tablet. The Transformer has <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/802.11n">WiFi</a> but no <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GSM_services#Data_transmission">mobile data</a>. Without a portable means of accessing a website, the lack of data plan would dramatically limit the usability of my tablet.
</p>
<p>
I have taken to <i>bookifying</i> websites that I have an interest in staying up to date with (eg: <a href="http://xkcd.com">XKCD</a>). For most sites, I only care about the newest postings. I convert the newest posting into an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPUB">epub</a> book, load it onto my tablet, and then read it using one an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ebook_reader">ebook reader</a>.
</p>
<p>
Besides bookifying the newest articles on <a href="http://lifehacker.com">LifeHacker</a>, I have also bookified entire websites.
</p>
<p>
The cool part is, this process requires a one-time configuration and then works automatically. That is, the entire web sites sit on my tablet and old website articles are automatically replaced by the new ones. 
<!-- more -->

</p></div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-2" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-2">The Process</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">

<p>The bookification process utilizes the following tools:
</p><ul>
<li>The <a href="http://www.wikipedia.com/Foss">FOSS</a> epub creation and library management tool <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calibre_(software)">Calibre</a>.
</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.jrtstudio.com/CheetahSync">Cheetah Sync</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File_synchronization">file-synchronization</a> application for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a>.
</li>
<li>The <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.flyersoft.moonreaderp&amp;feature=related_apps#?t=W251bGwsMSwxLDEwOSwiY29tLmZseWVyc29mdC5tb29ucmVhZGVycCJd">Moon+</a> Android book reader.
</li>
</ul>


<p>
Calibre comes packed with features for downloading new postings on a website, converting them to an epub book, and then managing the library it creates. It has nice extras such as updating sites on a customizable schedule and allowing you to specify how many ebooks of a site you wish to keep (eg: just today's publication or an entire week's worth).
</p>
<p>
Cheetah Sync provides WiFi folder synchronization between your desktop (Mac OS X or Windows) and your Android tablet. This synchronization can happen on a schedule or manually to reduce battery usage.
</p>
<p>
Moon+ is one of a large number of Android book readers. It seems to facilitate being used on a rotating library such as Calibre's by monitoring a directory on the file system and responding appropriately to changes.
</p>
<p>
The end product of this is the LifeHacker website on my Transformer:
</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<p><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8284/7576840720_3b50e3b359_z.jpg"  alt="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8284/7576840720_3b50e3b359_z.jpg" />
</p>
</div>

<p>
As a bonus, Calibre comes with a built-in epub book reader that you can run on your desktop:
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
<p><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8015/7576921304_54fbbc35b6.jpg"  alt="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8015/7576921304_54fbbc35b6.jpg" />
</p>
</div>

<p>
The output is less-cluttered that the site; seeming like a <a href="http://readability.com">Readibility</a> or <a href="http://instapaper.com">InstaPaper</a>
version of the all new content on the site.
</p>
</div>

</div>




<div id="outline-container-3" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-3">Books And Websites</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">

<p>Besides using Calibre to create epub books, it also does a good job of managing existing ones. For example, <a href="http://www.sapphiresteel.com">SapphireSteel Software</a> (whose name is an esoteric reference to a late 1970's British <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sapphire_&amp;_Steel">TV show</a>) have published an epub book called <a href="http://www.sapphiresteel.com/The-Little-Book-Of-Ruby">The Little Book Of Ruby</a>. I'm learning Ruby and sometimes it is nice to be able to look up something when I'm not near a WiFi connection and don't want to use my mobile WiFi hotspot as that tends to get costly quickly.
</p>
<p>
Calibre also provides a means for bookifying entire websites or a specified portion of them. This works by creating a temporary copy of the website on your computer and then converting it to epub format with Calibre.
</p>
<p>
Calibre provides its own <a href="http://manual.calibre-ebook.com/cli/web2disk.html">web2disk</a> utility that can download a website to your local disk. Sites such as <a href="http://www.teleread.com/drm/the-abcs-of-format-conversion-for-the-kindle-sony-and-nook-plus-some-calibre-tips/">this one</a> cover the details of this conversion. 
</p>
<p>
I happen to be familiar with the more fleible but more complex Linux program <a href="http://curl.haxx.se/docs/manpage.html">curl(1)</a> and tend to use that to download an entire website. This <a href="https://www.google.com/webhp?ie=UTF-8&amp;ion=1#hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=download+website+using+curl&amp;qscrl=1&amp;oq=download+website+using+curl&amp;fp=1">Google search</a> has numerous references on using curl to download a website.
</p>
<p>
While Moon+ is my preference for ebook news due to its responsiveness in dealing with an externally managed library, I prefer uploading my books to <a href="http://amazon.com">Amazon</a>'s Kindle library. For me, the Kindle's synchronization of bookmarks, notes, and current reading location are of much greater importance when I'm reading a book than when I'm reading a website. I use the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/feature.html/ref=kcp_and_ln_ar?docId=165849822">Kindle for Android</a> app on my tablet and smartphone and the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/feature.html/ref=sv_kstore_1?ie=UTF8&amp;docId=1000493771">Kindle for desktop or browser</a> from my computer.
</p>
<p>
While Kindle doesn't directly support the epub format, there are <a href="http://techsupport.foreverwarm.com/how-to-read-epub-books-on-your-kindle">simple directions</a> for converting epub ebooks to Kindle format using Calibre. This is a page from the <a href="http://www.orgmode.org">Org Mode</a> website ebook on my Transformer Kindle:
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
<p><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8167/7577094056_656f76bc81.jpg"  alt="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8167/7577094056_656f76bc81.jpg" />
</p>
</div>

</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blackberry's Manufacturer RIM Nearly RIP]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/03/31/rim-rip/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-31T20:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/03/31/rim-rip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<b>RIM No Longer A Viable Company</b>
</p>


<p>
<a href="http://bit.ly/HAtKtt">RIM</a>, arguably the manufacturer of the first successful smartphone, the <a href="http://bit.ly/HAub73">Blackberry</a>, has not only lost its market lead, but is facing a rather unpredictable future. RIM's new CEO, <a href="http://bit.ly/HAuOO6">Thorsten Heins</a>, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/rim-charts-risky-survival-plan-while-opening-door-to-sale/2012/03/31/gIQAJYZRnS_story.html?tid=pm_business_pop">has stated</a> that RIM is open to acquisition. At least for the short-term, his statements have led to a one-day, 5% bounce back of the stock price which was down 70% in the 12 months.
</p>


<p>
<b>RIM's History</b>
</p>


<p>
For those of you that are unaware of RIM's history, it got its start in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</a> as a <a href="http://bit.ly/H9vfx5">2-way pager</a> provider. In 1999, RIM moved into the smartphone market with its first Blackberry and immediately achieved market dominance. 
</p>




<!-- more -->




<p>
Factors that led to their dominance included:
</p>


<ul>
<li>Intelligent Marketing: One example was a giving away pre-1.0 Blackberries to attendees of the 1999 <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JavaOne">JavaOne</a> conference. I imagine that there wasn't a better set of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_release_life_cycle#Beta">beta testers</a> than the gadget geeks that attended JavaOne (myself include). 
</li>
<li>Sales Channels: RIM was selling its 2-way pagers to professionals who had a need to be in constant communication such as doctors, attorneys, business executives, and law enforcement. With the introduction of the Blackberry, RIM just added a better product to offer those same professionals. Sure it was more expensive, but 2-way pagers were already fairly costly. They were the perfect audience to market smartphones to.
</li>
<li>First To Market: In 1999, most mobile providers were focused on upgrading their networks from analog to digital. Once the digital networks were in place, new functionality such as internet access would be easy to providing. But upgrading networks takes time. It involves men climbing towers, FCC regulations, local zoning laws, etc. But RIM didn't have to do this.
</li>
</ul>




<p>
<b>RIM's Brilliance</b>
</p>


<p>
In what I consider a spectacular marketing and technological move, RIM started providing internet service over their existing 2-way pager network. While only a short-term solution as the 2-way pager network was designed for low-bandwidth usage, it was instantaneous. The first Blackberry was basically a 2-way pager with a good sized screen and full QWERTY keyboard. 
</p>


<p>
<b>What Went Wrong</b>
</p>


<p>
RIM's mistake was that they didn't learn from prior boom-to-bust technology companies. RIM seems to have perfectly followed the (mis)steps of Digital Electronics. While IBM has survived, it lost its market dominance in a sector, twice. The first time as a manufacture of mainframes in the 1970's and then again as a PC manufacturer in the 1980's. Apollo Computers, SGI, Xerox, all leaders at one time, are either gone or no longer of interest. 
</p>


<p>
All of these companies suffered from a similar set of mistakes including:
</p>


<ul>
<li>Overconfidence: Each company thought that they were invulnerable. IBM is perhaps the best example. In the 1970's, when an IT manager had to make a decision about what gigantic computer to buy, they often said "Nobody ever got fired for choosing IBM.". 
</li>
<li>Lack of Foresight: Technology and markets change and so too must your company. Clearly RIM, along with its arch-rival Palm, both missed the boat. Phones went from being personal communication devices to be tiny, fit-in-your-pocket, computers. 
</li>
<li>Unwillingness to Self-Cannibalize: In order to stay ahead of the technology market, you must be willing to come out with products that are better and cheaper than your existing products. HP and Goodyear are two companies that get this. Within a product line, HP routinely comes out with a better and cheaper printer than the one they currently have on the market. They know that it is going to kill sales of their existing printer. But HP also knows that when their customers need a new printer, it will be an HP printer. I know that Goodyear isn't considered a technology company, but their product, tires, involve high-tech materials and manufacturing processes. The CEO of Goodyear once asked how do you keep a company in business when you know that your next product is going to be cheaper, better, and last longer than your current product? While I think that HP and Goodyear would both prefer to keep selling their old products, they know better. It seems RIM didn't.
</li>
</ul>




<p>
<b>The Final Outcome</b>
</p>


<p>
In the end, RIM, the makers of the Blackberry that was a status symbol for business executives in the 1990's, has all but been put out of business by Apple, a waning computer company in 1990, and Google, a non-existent company in 1990. 
</p>


<p>
The trick to surviving in the high-tech marketplace is simple. All you need to do is realize that your market share is never safe, that there is always another company working on something that is better than what you have, and that you must act if you are fighting for your life, all-day, everyday. 
</p>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smartphones Everywhere]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/02/22/smartphones/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-22T13:38:14-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.neilsmithline.com/blog/2012/02/22/smartphones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Interpreting this chart from <a href="http://blog.nielsen.com/nielsenwire/online_mobile/survey-new-u-s-smartphone-growth-by-age-and-income/">Nielsen</a> (via <a href="http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2012/02/smartphone-buying-machine/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed:+wired/index+(Wired:+Index+3+(Top+Stories+2))">Wired</a>) does not require any great amount of effort.
</p>


<div style="text-align: center">
<p><img src="http://www.wired.com/images_blogs/epicenter/2012/02/Smartphone-Income-and-Age.jpg"  alt="http://www.wired.com/images_blogs/epicenter/2012/02/Smartphone-Income-and-Age.jpg" />
</p>
</div>




<p>
It can be summarized by any of the following sentences:
</p>


<ul>
<li>The greater your income the more likely you are to have a smartphone.
</li>
<li>Young adults are more likely to have smartphones than older adults.
</li>
<li>Smartphones are only for the young and get outgrown by the old. (Nah! But it is a valid interpretation of the chart.)
</li>
</ul>




<p>
But I think the graph can best be summarized by:
</p>


<div style="text-align: center">
<p><b>Smartphones are where it is at today; and tomorrow, even more so.</b>
</p>
</div>




<!-- more -->


<p>
Perhaps not the best grammar but I think it gets the point across. It becomes even more dramatic when you look at the number of people who have acquired smartphones in the past three months:
</p>


<div style="text-align: center">
<p><img src="http://blog.nielsen.com/nielsenwire/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/SmartPhone_Recent-acquirers-age1.png"  alt="http://blog.nielsen.com/nielsenwire/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/SmartPhone_Recent-acquirers-age1.png" />
</p>
</div>




<p>
As <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0059968/quotes">Robin</a> would <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batman_(TV_series)#.22Holy_.......2C_Batman.21.22">say</a>: Holy <a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/ubiquitous+computing?qsrc=2446">ubiquitous computing</a>, Batman!
</p>


<p>
It seems clear that this is where the money is. This means that some subset of technologies such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Html5">HTML5</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtuality_(computing)">virtual computing</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scala_(programming_language)">Scala</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadoop">Hadoop</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Web_Services">AWS</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Couchdb">CouchDB</a>, to name just a few, are going to be the technologies of tomorrow.
</p>


<p>
In my lifetime, I have seen computers revolutionize society in several different ways.
</p>


<dl>
<dt><a href="#Http-en.wikipedia.org-wiki-Back_office">Back office</a></dt><dd>Back office computerization led to the popularization of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automated_teller_machine">ATMs</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Credit_card">credit cards</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fed_Ex">Fed Ex</a> and its overnight delivery service, and set the stage for the online marketplace we are familiar with today.
</dd>
<dt><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_computer">Personal computers</a></dt><dd>Personal computers introduced computing to the public. When I was in school, I would get bonus points for typing my homework assignments. Today, homework assignments must be printed from a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word_processor">word processor</a> if not submitted electronically.
</dd>
<dt><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_wide_web">The web</a></dt><dd>The web, for the first time ever, connected the back office directly to consumers in the comfort of their own home. ATMs allowed you to get 24x7 access to your bank account, but you needed to be at an ATM. PCs gave you access to many digital technologies, but having multiple computers interact was difficult, slow, and frequently expensive. But throw in the web and suddenly: <b>BOOM!</b> You have the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Online_shopping">online shopping</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_gaming">video gaming</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_on_demand">video on demand</a> that we live in today.
</dd>
</dl>




<p>
As a diehard nerd, I'm thrilled to have lived through these technical revolutions. Not only have I lived through them, but I've had the honor of having been an early consumer and even helped develop some of them. So, with great joy, and without trying to sound too greedy, I am joyous that the next revolutionary wave is coming to shore. And it is called <i>ubiquitous computing</i>.
</p>


<p>
I don't claim to be the <a href="http://article.wn.com/view/2012/02/02/Did_the_Groundhog_see_his_shadow_2012_Punxsutawney_Phil_twee/">prognosticator of prognosticators</a>. <a href="http://www.wikipedia.com">Wikipedia</a>'s page on ubiquitous computing was created <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ubiquitous_computing&amp;action=history">two years ago</a>. I'm just happy to be around to be part of it and hope that I get a chance to <a href="http://bit.ly/zN6qBU">surf the wave</a>.
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
